A Guide to the Photographs, Series 1011-1081 FA438
Rockefeller Archive Center
Photographs, Series 1011-1081
1885-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
FA438
42 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.
Conditions Governing Access
Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement
Each collection or set of photographs in this guide has been assigned a four digit series number, as noted. Series represented in this guide span 1011 through 1081, and are representative of those collections which received archival processing prior to 2008.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid is an artificial compilation of photographic materials at RAC.
It is not a comprehensive representation of all photographic holdings available at the Rockefeller Archive Center.
Processing and description practices at RAC prior to 2008 assigned a four-digit series number to each collection of photographs. The term photographs was used broadly to encompass graphic materials and may also include a small selection of audio or video materials. This finding aid describes those photographic collections, arranged by Series Number.
While seperation of graphic materials from the body of their original collections remains a critical aspect of the care provided by RAC to address the specific needs and ensure the long-term preservation of these holdings, the practice of assigning four-digit series numbers was discontinued in 2008.
- Lawrence B. Dunham, ca. 1885-1957; 1011; 1 folder
  Scope and Contents
  Law enforcement, groups, recreation, boats, awards, ceremonies.
  Scope and Contents note
  57 photographs, consisting of portraits, portrayals of ceremonial occasions, yachting events, and Yale University class reunions.
  Biographical / Historical
  Lawrence Boardman Dunham was born in Newton, Massachusetts, on July 18, 1882, and received the Ph.B degree from Yale University in 1904. He graduated from the New York Law School in 1907 and entered into practice in New York City until 1913, when he was appointed Deputy Commissioner of Bridges for New York City. The following year, he was named Deputy Commissioner of the Police, a post he retained until 1922. On June 10, 1915, he married (Margaret) Vrayling Putnam; their family included three children.
  Dunham's tenure with the Police Department was interrupted by his service in the U.S. Army during World War I. In 1918 he served with the rank of Major in the intelligence division and was stationed primarily at Hoboken, New Jersey. Upon his resignation from the Police Department in 1922, he joined the G.M.P. Murphy Company, and until 1925 was president of the Caddo Central (later Clayton) Oil and Refining Company.
  From 1925 until 1928 Dunham was associated with the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, directing studies of crime and juvenile delinquency. For the next six years (1928-1934), he was Director of the Bureau of Social Hygiene, where he developed programs reflecting his interests while involved with the LSRM. During 1931-1932 he also served as a technical advisor to the U.S. delegation to the League of Nations Opium Convention in Geneva, Switzerland.
  Dunham acted as campaign manager in the Bronx for Fiorello H. LaGuardia's first mayoral contest in 1933. During the first 16 months of LaGuardia's term, he served as Executive Secretary to the Mayor. On April 16, 1935, he was appointed City Magistrate, and on September 23 of the same year was named to the Domestic Relations Court of New York City.
  In 1942, Judge Dunham reentered active service with the U.S. Army and was engaged in intelligence work with the General Staff Corps, serving with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. He directed counterespionage and anti-sabotage operations on both the east and west coast of the United States. In 1945 he was awarded the U.S. Legion of Merit. After the war, he retired from the bench, and died on August 8, 1959, at Plattsburgh, New York.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
  Dunham, Lawrence Boardman
  - Lawrence B. Dunham, c. 1885-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Edwin Embree, 1012; 3 folders
  Edwin Embree (1883-1950) was born in Osceola, Nebraska, and lived as a youth in Colorado, Wyoming and Kentucky. He graduated from Yale University in 1906 with a B.A. and then joined the staff of the New York Sun as a cub reporter assigned to police stations and theaters. In 1907 he accepted a position as assistant editor of the Yale Alumni Weekly and remained at Yale in a variety of administrative capacities until 1917. While at New Haven he continued his studies in philosophy and education and received an M.A. in 1913.
  In 1917 Mr. Embree joined The Rockefeller Foundation as Secretary under George E. Vincent. Interested in interracial relations, race development, human biology, and cultural anthropology, Embree became Director of the newly created Division of Studies in 1925, and developed some of these interests. He remained in that position until 1927 when he filled the position of Vice President of the Foundation.
  Pursuing his interests in interracial relations in 1927, Embree became Director of the Rosenwald Fund, a group which made appropriations to agencies working in the area of Negro welfare. After the depression the Fund concentrated on research and planning in connection with farm tenant problems. Several articles were written as a result of these studies which led to Federal legislation and the establishment of the Farm Security Administration. Having expended its resources, the Rosenwald Fund terminated in 1948. Embree then became President of the Liberian Foundation, a joint American-Liberian organization which assisted in the advancement of health, welfare and education in that country.
  Mr. Embree was the author of "Brown America, the story of a New Race," 1931; "Prospecting for Heaven," 1932; "American Negroes: A Handbook," 1932; "Indians of the Americas," 1939; "Brown Americans: the Story of a Tenth of the Nation," 1943; "Thirteen Against the Odds," 1944; and co-author of "Human Biology and Race Welfare," 1930.
  Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Australian Aborigines, Mounted on board, captions on back, severely faded, yellowed (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Indigenous peoples, Australia.
  - Australian Aborigines, 3 mounted on board, with captions, all severely faded (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stone Mountain, Georgia, Mounted on board with captions, severely faded (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Sculpture, landscapes.
- Estus H. Magoon, 1013
  Other Finding Aids
  For pertinent photographs please see:
  FA088 Estus H. Magoon photographs
  Magoon, Estus H.
- Will M. Myers, 1014; 2 folders
  Will Martin Myers (1911-1970) was born and raised in Bancroft, Kansas. He received a B.S. in Agronomy from Kansas State College in 1932 and an M.S. and Ph.D. in Plant Genetics from the University of Minnesota in 1934 and 1936.
  In 1937 Dr. Myers joined the United States Department of Agriculture as Geneticist at the Pasture Research Laboratory, State College, Pennsylvania. After World War II he was Geneticist and Consultant with the Far Eastern Command in Japan. He returned to the USDA as Head of the Division of Forage Crops and Diseases and then as Director of Field Crops Research at Beltsville, Maryland. From 1950-1952 Dr. Myers organized the Sixth International Grasslands Conference and later was Chairman of the U.S. Delegation to the Seventh International Grasslands Conference in 1956. After leaving the Department of Agriculture in 1952, Dr. Myers became Head of the Department of Agronomy and Plant Genetics at the University of Minnesota. He became Dean of the Office of International Programs in 1963.
  Dr. Myers had been a consultant to The Rockefeller Foundation since 1954 and spent 1959-1960 in India in that capacity. As Associate Director of Agricultural Sciences in 1964 he also became Director of the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture in Ibadan from 1965-1967. With the Institute formally organized in 1968, he became Chairman of the Board. In 1967 Dr. Myers became Vice-President of the Foundation with interests in the areas of Medical and Natural Sciences, Agriculture, and programs oriented toward University Development, Population, Conquest of Hunger, and Quality of the Environment.
  Dr. Myers had many associations, some of which were Chairman, Committee on Agricultural Science, USDA; Chairman, Agricultural Research Facilities Needs Committee, USDA; Chairman, Latin American Science Board National Academy of Sciences; Member, U.S. National Commission, United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO); Consultant, Ford Foundation; Consultant, Office of Science and Technology, Executive Office of the President; Science Advisor to Assistant Administrator, Latin American Bureau, AID and Coordinator, Alliance for Progress, 1962; Member, U.S. Delegation to the United Nations Conference on Application of Science and Technology in Assistance to Developing Nations, 1963; Chairman, Crops Division, 1946, Vice President 1957, President 1958, American Society of Agronomy.
  Myers, Will M.
  - William M. Myers, Some have captions attached or typed on back, 1 with slight fading, some curling (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Ceremonies, awards, speeches, conferences, agriculture, corn, group photo.
  - Farm Machinery, Captions attached to back, 5 with adhesive staining (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Agriculture, farming, machines.
- Spelman Fund of New York, 1015
  The Spelman Fund of New York was chartered as a corporation on December 27, 1928, exclusively for "charitable, scientific and educational purposes including the advancement and diffusion of knowledge concerning child life, the improvement of interracial relations and cooperation with public agencies."
  $10,000,000 was provided for The Spelman Fund by the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial shortly after the latter organization merged with The Rockefeller Foundation in 1929. The Memorial had developed a broad program in child study and interracial relations. Though the Fund continued to support some of the agencies previously supported by the Memorial for the duration of the particular grant, the main program of the Fund was in the area of public administration and intergovernmental relations. This was an area the Memorial had just begun to develop in its program, and it soon became the primary interest of the Fund. The Fund worked to improve the technical aspects of public administration. They supported activities which would improve exchange of technical information and experience and also activities of research to discover improved methods and techniques of organization.
  Many major appropriations were made to the "1313" agencies, i.e., the American Association of Public Welfare Officials, the American Legislators Association, the American Municipal Association, the American Public Welfare Association, the American Public Works Association, the American Society of Planning Officials, the Civil Service Assembly, the Council of State Governments, the Federation of Tax Administrators, the International City Managers Association, the Municipal Financial Officers Association, the National Association of Housing Officials, the Public Administration Clearing House and the Public Administration Service. These groups were brought together in Chicago in 1932, and later in a building on the campus of the University of Chicago. The address was 1313 E. 60th Street, hence the name.
  The final grant of unexpended funds was made to the Public Administration Clearing House, the nerve center of the "1313" agencies, and in 1949 the Fund was dissolved.
  Spelman Fund
  - Spelman Fund of New York, Some mounted on board, captions on back, 2 fading; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Buildings, construction, conferences, staff.
- Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, 1016; 13 folders
  The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was incorporated in October 1918, for general philanthropic purposes. It was not geographically limited and indeed was international, especially in its early emphasis on emergency relief. A memorial to Laura Spelman Rockefeller, the first thought for a program was the welfare of women and children, but philanthropy is not easily granted along divisions of age or sex and so for the first few years of the Memorial's existence the program was fluid. W. S. Richardson was the main executive during the years 1918-1922. The Memorial worked through John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s office then, and many of the Memorial files were interwoven with other office files.
  In 1922 Beardsley Ruml became director of the Memorial and a long-range program was developed. Appropriations were still made in the areas of leisure, public health, and emergency relief, but from 1922 through the end of the Memorial's independent existence, the social sciences and welfare, child study and parent education, and interracial relations became primary interests. Research was sponsored, but not as an end unto itself; grants were made for demonstrations, concrete applications of newly gained knowledge. The aim of the entire program was to achieve concrete improvement in the conditions of life and to contribute realistically to public welfare.
  On January 3, 1929, the Memorial consolidated with The Rockefeller Foundation and became its division of Social Sciences. A final grant of $10,000,000 was made to the Spelman Fund of New York, an independently incorporated board, to administer some appropriations in child study, parent education, and interracial relations. The Spelman Fund went on to continue the Memorial's fledgling interest in public administration as its main emphasis.
  Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
  - League of Red Cross Societies - Junior Red Cross, 1920s; 1 yellowing, mounted on board, caption on back (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Junior Red Cross manual training course for teachers, Yugoslavia.
    Separated Materials note
    Removed from Series 3.1 - Appropriations - Public Health, Box 2, Folders 17-21
  - New York Tuberculosis Association (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Classrooms, children, diseases, tuberculosis, crafts, trade skills.
    Removed from Series 3.1 - Appropriations - Public Health, Box 4, Folders 48-49
  - Emergency Relief - Russian Zemstvos (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Zemstvos, war, children, schools.
    Removed from Series 3.3 - Appropriations - Emergency Relief, Box 9, Folders 108-110
  - American Association of Museums - Yosemite, mounted on board, captions on back, 2 fading (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Museums, construction.
    Removed from Series 3.4 - Appropriations - Leisure, Box 11, Folders 121-122
  - YMCA College, Chicago, Mounted on board, captions on back, 1 yellowed (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Schools, gymnasiums, classrooms, Young Men's Christian Association.
    Removed from Series 3.4 - Appropriations - Leisure, Box 19, Folders 206-208
  - National Research Council - Deaf Projects, 1922; Mounted on board, caption on back, some silvering, image fading (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Removed from Series 3.6 - Appropriations - Social Studies, Box 58, Folders 624-628
  - Emergency Relief - Near East, Mounted on board, captions on back, severe yellowing, image loss, silvering (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Refugees, children, orphanages, war.
    Removed from Series 3.3 - Appropriations - Emergency Relief, Box 8, Folders 100-103 and Box 9, Folder 104
  - Emergency Relief - Near East (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Children, orphanages, refugees, war, schools, trade skills.
  - Neighborhood Teacher's Association, Mounted on board, captions on back, yellowing, silvering, image fading (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Trade skills, weaving, classrooms, libraries, holidays.
    Removed from Series 3.7 - Appropriations - Social Welfare, Box 84, Folders 881-890.
  - City Housing Corporation, New York City, Mounted on board, caption on back, yellowing (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Buildings.
    Removed from Series 3.7 - Appropriations - Social Welfare, Box 82, Folder 860 - Housing Situation in New York City.
  - People's Institute, New York City, Mounted on board, captions on back, yellowing, fading, silvering (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Community work, weaving.
    Removed from Series 3.7 - Appropriations - Social Welfare, Box 85, Folder 898 and Box 86, Folders 899-901.
  - Boy Scouts of America - Negro, Mounted on board, caption on back, loss of image highlight, fading (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Segregation, clubs.
    Removed from Series 3.8 - Appropriations - Interracial Relations, Box 96, Folders 969-971.
  - Negro Health - West Virginia, Mounted on board, captions on back, creased, yellowed, fading (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Segregation, hospitals, insanity.
    Removed from Series 3.8 - Appropriations - Interracial Relations, Box 100, Folder 1017.
- Bureau of Social Hygiene, 1017; 5 folders
  The Bureau of Social Hygiene resulted from the appointment of John D. Rockefeller, Jr., to a Special Grand Jury to investigate white slavery in New York City in 1910. In conferences taken in the course of this investigation, Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., became convinced that for a lasting improvement of conditions a permanent organization was needed. On March 22, 1911, The Committee of Three, including Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., Paul Warburg, and Starr Murphy, met. The name "Bureau of Social Hygiene" was first used in October of that year, but not consistently until 1913.
  In 1913 the Bureau was incorporated and its purpose was stated as "...the study, amelioration, and prevention of those social conditions, crimes, and diseases which adversely affect the well being of society, with special reference to prostitution and the evils associated therewith." The Bureau would engage in research and education, publish reports, and employ and/or cooperate with other public or private agencies to obtain these goals. The emphasis in the years from 1911 until the reorganization of 1928 was mainly on prostitution, the control of vice, and, through that, the relationships to police organization. Narcotics was also an early interest. Throughout these early years, Katherine Bement Davis, Commissioner of Charities and Correction of New York and later Superintendent of Bedford Hills Reformatory, guided the Bureau as General Secretary.
  Miss Davis resigned in 1928 and Lawrence B. Dunham was appointed Director. Under Mr. Dunham's administration, from 1928-1934, the Bureau developed a broadened interest in criminology. In 1929 the certificate of incorporation was amended and the emphasis on prostitution was dropped. Criminology embraced crime reporting, police training and education, penology, criminal law, and juvenile delinquency. While studies and projects were still conducted in narcotics and social hygiene, the main thrust of the organization was crime and criminology.
  The Bureau functioned through grants. It was not a foundation and had no set endowment. In the very early years of its existence, financial backing came from several sources including Paul Warburg, the New York Foundation, and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., although throughout the history of the Bureau, Mr. Rockefeller, Jr., was always the main contributor. Grants were occasionally channeled through the Bureau from the Spelman Fund of New York and the Rockefeller Foundation.
  Grants were made by the Bureau for a variety of types of work. Research studies were conducted, such as the Institute of Criminology and the Crew Study; books were published, such as "European Police Systems" and "Policewoman's Handbook"; fellowships were given, as were the fellowships in prison study; and experiments were conducted at the Massachusetts State Prison Colony and the Laboratory of Social Hygiene at Bedford Hills. Grants were most often long range covering periods of from three to five years. Although the Bureau did not interfere in the conduct of a project once money had been granted, it was careful in its selection of projects and kept in close touch during the life of the project.
  The Bureau ceased making new appropriations in 1934 and by mid-1937 all the previous commitments had been brought to a close. Annual meetings were held until 1940 when the Bureau was dissolved on November 13th.
  Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
  - Decline of the Prison Population in England, Mounted on board, caption on back, slight fading (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Prisons, Germany.
  - European Police Systems - France, Mounted on board, captions on back, some fading, loss of image highlight (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Law enforcement, vehicles.
  - European Police Systems, Mounted on board, captions on back, light fading (Box 3, Folder 0029A)
    Law enforcement, fingerprints, England, Germany, Austria.
  - Narcotics, Mounted on board, caption on back, fading (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Merck, industry, Germany.
  - New York Police Psychopathic Laboratory, Mounted on board, caption on back, creasing, fading (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Insanity, law enforcement.
- John A. Ferrell, 1018; 2 folders
  John Atkinson Ferrell was born in Clinton, North Carolina, in December 1880. He received a B.S. from the University of North Carolina in 1902, an M.D. in 1907, and a Dr.P.H. from Johns Hopkins University in 1919.
  From 1902-1905 Dr. Ferrell taught school and was County Superintendent of Schools in Sampson County, North Carolina. In 1907 he became County Superintendent of Health there. From 1910-1913 Dr. Ferrell was associated with the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission and was State Director for North Carolina. In 1914 Dr. Ferrell became Associate Director of the International Health Division of The Rockefeller Foundation and served in that capacity until his retirement in 1944. Dr. Ferrell then became Medical Director of the Markle Foundation from 1944-1946. He was also Executive Secretary of the North Carolina Medical Care Commission from 1946-1957.
  Dr. Ferrell was a member of the American Medical Association, the Southern Medical Association, the National Malaria Committee of which he was Chairman in 1924, the Medical Society of the State of North Carolina for which he was Secretary from 1911-1914, the Medical Society of Wake County, North Carolina, the American Public Health Association of which he was President in 1933 and Chairman of the Board from 1935-1939. He was an honorary life member of the Conference of State and Provincial Health Authorities of North America and the Canadian Public Health Association.